So we're 1665, pretty high
rated. 1647 is our opponent. Let's go e
four. And we're mostly still meeting. Okay, so c five.
And we've been playing the smith mora with a lot of success in the speedrun.
Let's continue that practice. And accepted smithmora.
Let's go. Okay. E five. Now, I've actually
seen this move a lot at this level, which is new to me because,
I mean, it's a very anti positional move. It weakens the d five square tremendously.
Black does sometimes play this move in the smith mora, but never this early.
We want to develop our pieces normally, as we normally do in the smithmora.
And we have massive control, we have total control over the square.
So we want to start by getting the bishop out to c
four. And we can also think about putting early pressure on
the f seven pond. We can do that by getting the queen out to b
three. I think everybody's familiar with this idea by now. When the pawn on c
two is sacrificed early, queen b three related ideas
become a thing. And speaking of which, queen b
three here is very possible, but we could also amend that
in a slightly more tactical way. So what is possible
here on the theme of queen b three?
So we can start with the ship takes off. Stop, stop and check. There's a
very interesting line there. After queen b three, check. Black can
actually play d five using the tempo that he
has while we're taking this bishop to shove
this pawn down to d four. So the crazy thing
is that I actually think queen b three
might be better than bishop takes f seven check in this
particular instance. So we're actually going to go queen b three. And after the
game, I'll show you why I'm insistent on playing it
this way. Now, which piece do we want to recapture with? Our opponent
probably feels relieved that we didn't take on f seven, but I think that this
is much more likely to result in a quick win. But we definitely want
to take with the pawn. We want to keep the battery alive and we want
to keep the pressure on f seven. In addition, taking with the pawn gives this
dark squared bishop a very, very powerful developing square
on a three. We could put the bishop there right now, but our
opponent is left f seven hanging. We're definitely taking that.
And I'm thinking that we could follow up by playing bishop. Bay three check.
And this is going to get really dicey for black really,
really fast. Okay, so this is not GG yet,
by the way. This is not quite as easy as it may appear.
As you'll see, black has a couple of defensive options. But I think if we
develop properly, we should be close to winning. Let's start with bishop
a three check. And then after d six, which is forced. Let's think.
So the first option would be to put more pressure
on the d six pond. This seems like a logical thing to do. So probably
some of you are thinking, let's go rook d one. The problem with
rook d one is black has knight takes e four,
simultaneously taking that pawn and then defending d
six. So we have to find a response to night takes c four.
Now, I actually think that the response
to night takes. Okay, there's an interesting line
there that I'm trying to puzzle out. So rookie one,
night 64 is one option. We could investigate that further.
The other option is to simply develop
our pieces. We could just play knight f three and castle and hold
off on attacking the d six pawn until we're fully developed.
But my intuition is telling me that rook
d one has to be the move, and there has to be something. After 964,
we'll figure out what it is if black plays it. But I'm just
going to go rook d one intuitively, and then we'll cross that bridge if we
get there. Okay, so we have gotten there,
and this is, I think, an instructive moment because most people are
probably thinking, let's get rid of this knight. So you're thinking of f three
or queen d five. But neither of these moves seems as convincing to
me as perhaps it does to you because black will have
ways of counterattacking the f seven bishops. So, for example,
if white plays f three, black has the nasty move,
queen out to f six. And then if you calculate f
takes e four, queen takes f seven.
That is still a little bit uncertain, but in that
line, I actually think white is able to transform the position
into a very favorable end game. So f three is
one very viable option. Let's just go f three. Let's play this simple.
In an actual over the board game, I would very seriously
consider playing night f three and just getting our pieces out,
basically keeping the tension and then trying to castle. Okay,
queen h four, check. I had a feeling that black would play this, but it's
not good. We go g three. And if black takes on g three,
then there's just checkmate on d six.
So let's see if black is able to figure yeah, he is able to figure
out the best move, which is queen f six. And now I think that we
have okay, so we've got a couple of options here.
This is not GG yet. I mean, black is somehow he's holding on,
which is pretty incredible. I think that we need to transform
our advantage right now. We have this attack. What we need to do is
just take the nine on e four and then take the pawn on d six,
either with the rook or with the bishop. And we'll probably end up getting
some sort of an end game where we're up upon and we have a
tremendous initiative. So you got to be able to do that when you're attacking
and say, okay, this form of the attack isn't working out
exactly like I wanted it to. So we're going to take the attack and then
transform it into a different type of advantage. Now, how should
we take on D six? We have two approaches here. The one hand, we could
take with the bishop and then collect Blacks pawns. We could play bishop takes
and then bishop takes C five. On the other hand, we could say, I don't
care as much about the E five pond. I care more about the
initiative against Black sking. I like rook takes V six. I feel like this contains
a lot more pizazz because it sets up a potential discovery
and we'll be able to win the E five pond when
we want. So that pond on e five is a sitting duck. We can get
our Night out to have to be later. I don't think we'll have a problem
winning that pond. I think we need to put the emphasis on quick development
and see how far that can get us. Okay. Queen takes b. Three.
Our opponent continues to play this pretty accurately. A six, B three,
and kingdom is correct also. Okay, so we need to get our knight out
to f three. And now after nine C six, black is actually holding the
balance pretty nicely. So let's complete our development. Let's castle,
and let's continue trying to put pressure on Black in this end
game. I'm very impressed with our opponent's defensive capabilities here.
Maybe we should have taken with the bishop after all. But something tells me that
this position is very, very hard to play for Black. We have a rook that's
sandwiched on D six, and we need to keep the attack going. We cannot
waste time, and we cannot let Black keep consolidating. So what move
allows us to keep the initiative going? This is a very natural move
to me because it creates a lot more threats.
And that moves night out to G five. Exactly. So the knight
can potentially maneuver to e six. It can also
go to f seven. I mean, there's a lot of options here. Rook d eight.
So here are very important to avoid taking on D eight. You might think,
oh, we take on D eight and then go night f seven of the fork.
But after rook takes d eight, black and take back with a knight, then we
won't be able to get our knight into f seven. So the way we want
to play this is to go with the immediate night f
seven. Now, this isn't exactly a fork because obviously black
plays rook takes six. Now, interesting question.
What do we recapture with this is actually a very tricky question
because I feel like some of you might intuitively gravitate toward taking
with the bishop because it keeps the attack on the rook on H
eight. But if you calculate that out, bishop takes D six,
black plays rook G eight, and yes, we win the pawn on E five.
But you have to remember that in the end game, an extra pawn isn't always
the end of the world. And what's going to end up happening is that you
get an opposite colored bishop endgame where Black is able to get his
pieces out. A much better option is to take with the knight for two reasons.
First of all, this is a fork, so we still are able to win a
pawn. But the most important reason is that we paved the way for
the rook to infiltrate to F seven, which is exactly what we're going
to do right now. And we're going to end up winning a lot more than
just one pawn. We're probably going to end up winning two pawns,
and we're going to get a huge attack against Black king. So which pawn do
we take first? Well, if you compare, we can take b seven with
the rook, or we can take G seven with the rook. Well,
think about it. Obviously we should take G seven with the rook because that attacks
the bishop. And then we can take B seven with the knight
in order to prevent Black from putting his rook on f eight. Notice what Black
just did there? He's trying to checkmate us on f one. That's a tricky idea,
but our bishop is preventing the rook from coming to FA.
So now knight takes B seven. We've got our own mating ideas. Knight C five
is very, very close to mate, so we should be able to finish
this one off pretty smoothly. That Night on C six has also
lost its supporting pawn. So the move rook C seven could
end up being very, very strong. The Night simply doesn't have
a lot of breathing room or squares to go to.
Does that make sense? So Black is down
two ponds, and we've got the king fully surrounded
king F six. And as we discussed, where should the rook
go? Well, there's only one square available to the rook, and it's C seven,
right? It's literally the only move. Literally the only move.
Every other square is controlled by Blacks pieces. D seven is controlled by the bishop.
And now knight D eight loses on the spot. I won't tell you why just
yet in case he plays it. Knight B
eight is probably the only move for blackened. Okay?
Our opponent finds it now in such positions.
On the one hand, you have to play aggressively
and actively, but on the other hand, it's important not to rush too
much and to make improving moves when possible so that we
don't have to worry about various headaches. So this is a good example,
right? The king on G one, black has this constant idea of putting
a rook on up one and checkmating us I don't want to deal with that
headache, particularly in time pressure. So one thing we could do to improve our
position is just get the king to E three, a very safe central
square, and then we could worry about picking up the rest of Black spawns.
So we make our improvements first. This helps us survive time
pressure. Let's go king e three. Forget about everything else, and then we're going
to start worrying about bishop D six and knight back to C five and other
moves that aim to win blacks other pawns. This is
a nice example of sort of Russian school chess.
You can call it whatever you want, but it's this idea of not
making improvements first before you
barrel into complications. Night, d seven.
Okay, so lots of options here. Lots of options here.
We could go night back to D six and try to go to F seven.
I like the concept of trading nights here since we're up two pawns,
an opposite colored bishop end game doesn't worry me too much. I feel like it's
already going to be totally winning. And we're very likely to win a third
pawn because black Scott pawns all over the board. They're all scattered. They're all
weak. We're definitely going to win a third pawn here. Okay. Knight b six.
And case in point, we can take a seven. And I'm hoping that black
plays rook D eight because we have a really, really pretty tactic if rook
D eight happens. Something tells me, though, that he might play rook C eight.
Okay, so we have a third pawn in the bag. We've got connected passers,
which we can start pushing on the very next move. We can play C four,
and then we can move the night back and just keep pushing the CPA.
That's the simplest plan. Very simple. I mean, it's easy to convert these
endgame, so if you don't blunder, anything goes. Work a eight. I mean, that plays
right into our hands. At this point, we're up three pawns, and we're actually even
going to be up four. If you think about it, the E five pawn is
a total sitting dark. How can we combine our bishop and knight
in order to win the E five pond? What two moves can we make in
order to go up four pawns? Yes. We can start with 93,
not 97, because the bishop is covering that square.
Don't forget about these. And now Bishop D six. And now we're up four
pawns and the game is over.
97 would have hung the night. Okay, bishop 65.
Check. And that's it. Now we start
pushing our pawns in no particular order. It doesn't really matter. I would even bring
the king up to D four just to help supervise the
progress of the pawns. And then we can continue pushing C.
We can push indiscriminately. All of our pieces are defending each other.
We really don't have to worry about anything else.
Just keep pushing. B five. C five, c four. The only thing is, Bishop B
two might happen, and then we're going to have to move our Bishop. But that's
the only threat that Black can make. Okay, c five and
then C six. And then b. Six. Okay.
This is pretty easy and pretty fun.
Thank you, Burritos Galore. Okay, knight takes C five. Check. And now we're also
winning the Bishop on top of everything else. That was a nice game.
That was not easy at all. And our opponent defended very, very well.
So I'm sure that I probably had more efficient
ways to win right out of the opening. But we can take a
look with an engine. Actually, we can take a look with an engine just because
this game in particular, I feel like there was a lot of
tactical action, and it would be a
good idea to see where I went wrong. I'm sure I made quite a few
mistakes and didn't exploit this in the best way. So let's
see. Okay, the accuracy is not bad.
Maybe it wasn't as bad as I had thought.
Okay, so let's see.
So, yeah, e five is a big mistake.
I don't know why. It's like not giving me the kind of
review that I want. Okay, anyways, so queen B
three is one of the top moves. I wanted
to show why Bishop takes F seven check is wrong.
This is a very instructive moment, and I can already tell by the
email bar that it's wrong. So I've shut down the computer lines for the time
being because I want people to think of this on their own. Okay, so queen
b three. Check. Now, the way you might be thinking of this is, okay,
the King moves away. We take on before we've restored
material equality. The King has lost castling rights. We have all of
the advantages of our position, but in this position,
black has a really cool resource. And if you were listening carefully,
I actually mentioned it during the game, black can play the move D
five. And the way that this works is what? White has to waste a tempo
recapturing Bishop because we sacrificed it. And while
we do that, black pushes this pawn down to D four.
Maybe. Actually, black starts with NC. Six. If we look at the computer revolt.
Yeah, NC six is a much better idea here, developing with tempo.
And if the queen drops back to B three, trying to pin the pond in
Black as night, d four. So all of a sudden, Black gets this initiative because
we had to waste time capturing Bishop. So this very concrete tactical
reason actually means that Bishop takes F seven is a
bad move. And Queen D three is correct, as you can see. Okay, so bishop
c? Three, B-C-N-F six. And, yeah, this is completely winning. So bishop B three,
check. D. Knight takes C four.
And here we didn't find the correct idea.
F three is a pretty significant mistake. It's still winning.
The best move, though, was bishop back to D five.
Okay, so here's what I missed. I completely forgot that we're also attacking B
seven. I just forgot that that pawn is hanging. I forgot that pawn
is saying the reason I rejected bishop B five is because it blocks the rooks
contact with the D six pawn. And I didn't realize that, for example,
in this line, bishop C five, DC. And then bishop takes B seven wins the
game because it's an attack on the queen and an attack on the rook.
I just forgot about the B seven pawn. This just shows you how important
it is not to be narrow minded when you're attacking and
to pay attention to all potential pressure points in the position.
So bishop D five is one winning move. The other is the same idea.
Bishop h five. And then bishop F three, again skewering the knight
in the B seven pawn. So this B seven pawn is quite pivotal to the
correct winning path. Bishop B five is a really nice move.
It's very clinical, very surgical. So f three
queen h queen f six.
And again, F 64 mistake. At this
point, I had already kind of settled on this end game, and this actually loses
most of white's advantage. So not a good job converting this by me.
Again, we should have gone to shifty five. But again, I had forgotten about the
b seven pun. I wasn't looking at it. This just shows you that tunnel vision
happens at my level as well. I completely tunnel vision this position. I wasn't even
looking at this pond. I forgot that the queen was making contact with it.
And the other winning move is bishop H five. And if knight C five
oh, my goodness. Rook takes D six. Look at that tactic. What a move.
Knight takes me through rook D eight is checkmate. Queen Takes
d six. Queen f seven is checkmate. So the
position had a lot more tactical potential than I had realized.
And this is bishop h five is winning on
the spot. Black has to give up the knight, and it's over.
And by the way, folks, knight takes G three doesn't
work because the bishop takes V six, and black has to give the queen up.
So very instruct. Just shows you that. I don't know what this shows exactly,
but I had already kind of made up my mind to go
for this end game, and I thought, white is like winning here,
when in fact, it's the advantage is quite small.
The advantage is quite small. Thank you. A voice for the two months. And apparently
the move, the only move to keep a black position under control is king
F seven, which looks completely counterintuitive because it keeps the
king on the F file, which looks counterproductive
because white is going to castle. But the point is, you go rookie eight.
And if White Castles, you tuck the king away on G
eight, it's like an artificial castle. And if White plays knight takes C
five. Obviously you can't take because of checkmate.
Bishop H three, rook f two. And Black is
able to get all of his pieces out. Knight c six. Knight takes C
six, rook takes C four. Intermezzo threatening. Rookie one.
Checkmate. This is how computers play. And apparently black equalizes here.
So this is obviously one of the dangers of analyzing with an engine is
like, now you think, oh, this was all pretty easy.
I guess nobody's actually thinking that, though. And kingfseven is
not a move I would even expect the GM to play. I was positive that
king E eight is the only move. Yeah, brilliant.
Blind king F seven, rookie eight. All of sudden, Black artificially castles with
no other pieces developed, and Black is just, okay,
so king E eight, nine, F three. And at this point, Black position sucks castles.
Bishop G four, bishop G four is another inaccuracy. This allows the knight to
get into G five. And after knight F seven, I think Black never had any
more chances. Takes, takes. And here, I think we played very accurately.
Rookie seven, bishop H three, knight B seven, rook C seven,
king F two. And you notice that king F two is among the top moves.
So the computer also approves of this kind of play. NC five.
Yeah, and I think we never really let Black go after that.
Wow, a lot was packed into those 1st 1015 moves.
A lot was packed into the first 1015 moves.
Wait, 98 here. Because of Bishop B. Seven. Check. With a
fork. There was a nice tactic a little bit later on
when we were already completely winning. I was hoping that Black would go rook
D eight. Can somebody find an elegant
way to win? More material here? Obviously, we can take on age seven, and this
is completely winning. There's a cool little trick here.
Who sees it?
Yeah. 96, check. Bishop takes c six. Bishop B.
Seven. Check. With a fork. Using both minor pieces to win the
rook, that's actually kind of cool.
So the moral of the story is that I made up my mind,
which, first of all, don't automatically go for these
kinds of tactics because they can be wrong. In this case, queen B three is
correct. Made up my mind too quickly about going for that
end game rather than evaluating the options and looking at all sides of the
board when you're attacking. And the funny thing is, I talk to my students
often about this, this idea that when you're attacking, it's so easy to tunnel
vision one side of the board and to forget
that something on the other side of the board, such as a hanging piece,
could play a very direct role in the
attack. One way or another because obviously the board is interconnected and
I have a good example of one of my games where I was able to
apply that and win. So basically
it's a case of attack on both sides of
the board. So I got this attack down the H file. As you can
see, I started pushing my HPA in this position and then
I traded ponds, I opened up the H file and I got my pieces there.
So after king G seven, I did something cool. Who can tell me what
is the fastest way of getting a rook to the H file?
This is a very straightforward concept, but just as a little warm up exercise,
and obviously I'm ignoring the E seven pine. I don't give a pun.
The only thing I care about is getting the rook to the H file.
So we take the horsey forcing DC, and now we
just go Nd two. Very good. Not bishop d three. Mathematically,
taking the knight is the fastest way because this forces Black to respond.
OK, so we got a rook to H one. So here it's important to
resist the urge to give the check because it actually helps Black skin
go where he wants to go anyway. So we get the knight into the attack
and in this position I found a very, very nice tactic that's very directly based
on something on the other side of the board. And I'll give you guys a
chance to think about this wipe to play and find a crushing
tactical blow on the kingside. There's just not that much that you
can do, which I think helps people out. There's something on the
king side that white can do. It's not e six. E six there's. Bishop takes
E six and black survives.
Yeah, very good. Knight takes g six.
And the point is this, if black plays king
takes G six and this is where the lesson is
applied, we don't meet the king. That's not the point of
the combination. We go queen age five, check. And all of a sudden we
play E takes F six, check and whoop, the queen on 85 is hanging and
white wins the queen. So noticing that queen is crucial,
and if black plays knight takes G six, then we give queen H seven,
check. And then we take the knight. And we went easily.
So something similar happened in the game. My opponent played b three.
I basically ignored it. I took it and then played queen H five BC.
King takes C two, knight takes C six. And now the sexiest
move of the game. My opponent actually didn't see this for some reason. He was
expecting queen h seven. Check. That's not what I did, though. What did I
do? I played e six check. And he resigned
because the queen is lost on a five.
So the importance of the other side
of the board when you're attacking,
it cannot be overstated. So back to the speedrung
game. fullboard vision. And here looking at the pond on B seven was
critical playing Bishop D five, noticing that this pond being hanging is
the key to the victory for White. Okay, guys, that concludes
the analysis, and I think that is
going to conclude the stream. Hope you enjoyed. See you
guys later. Thank you so much for the support. Thanks for hanging out, everybody.